All right, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is ל״ד. Lamed
Dalet. It is the last דף daf of this פרק perek and
of the first half of ברכות Berachot which deals with שמע Shema
and שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. Tomorrow we will begin dealing with issues
about ברכות berachot on food and other forms of ברכות. berachot. We
had just mentioned yesterday the issue about מודים מודים, Modim Modim, repeating
מודים Modim twice and that that's a problem because it looks like
some type of a dualism. I just wanted to end that discussion
by looking quickly at a תוספות Tosafot which is in general relevant
and also relevant for this time of year. תוספות Tosafot on the
top of ל״ד עמוד א׳ Lamed Dalet Amud Aleph says אמר פסוקא
פסוקא וכפלה. amar psuka psuka vekafla. So there's a question which is
worse: to repeat each word or to repeat each פסוק. pasuk. But
anyway, he says if you look two lines down in the narrow
lines, ואותם בני אדם שאומרים ב׳ או ג׳ פעמים שמע ישראל ביום
הכיפורים. Ve-otam bnei adam she-omrim beis o gimmel pe'amim Shema Yisrael be-Yom
HaKippurim. Okay, שמע ישראל ה׳ אלהינו ה׳ אחד. Shema Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu
Hashem Echad.
So some people actually did that multiple times, maybe when we do
it now, you know, when you take out the ספרי תורה, Sifrei
Torah, it doesn't exactly say when that would be,
but anyway it was not clear. משתקין אותם, meshaskin otam, you silence
them. כפירוש רש״י, kefirush Rashi, because רש״י Rashi says that the whole
problem of saying שמע Shema twice is repeating the whole פסוק. pasuk.
כפירוש ר״ח, kefirush R"Ch, מגונה היה, meguna hayah, even if that's not
how you read the גמרא, Gemara, maybe you don't silence them but
it's still it's still like, you know, inappropriate, it's still to be
looked down upon, so we should not do that. או, O, then
he says maybe here's a way we could defend the practice. שמא
לא חשיב אלא כשקורא קריאת שמע בעונתה, Shema lo chashiv ela kshe-koreh
Krias Shema be-onatah, קבלת עול מלכות שמים. Kabalas Ol Malchus Shamayim. Maybe
it's only a problem in the context of the מצוה mitzvah of
קריאת שמע Krias Shema where it's about accepting the yoke of heaven
and there in particular we're sensitive to this because it might look
like, you know, like some aspect of dualism. So, you know, dualism
is a problem in general, but maybe we have a heightened concern
when it's in the context of the מצוה mitzvah of שמע Shema
and קבלת עול מלכות שמים. Kabalas Ol Malchus Shamayim. So maybe we
can defend the practice. ומכל מקום טוב שלא לומר. U-mikol makom tov
shelo lomar. You still whatever, either way, play it safe. Don't repeat
שמע Shema multiple times. אך מה שאומרים ה׳ הוא האלהים ז׳ פעמים,
Ach mah she-omrim Hashem Hu HaElokim zayin pe'amim, right?
You know the practice, ה׳ הוא האלהים ה׳ הוא האלהים, Hashem Hu
HaElokim Hashem Hu HaElokim, right? So he says ביום הכיפורים ויום הערבה.
be-Yom HaKippurim ve-Yom HaArava. What's יום הערבה? Yom HaArava? הושענא רבה. Hoshana
Rabba. כנגד ז׳ רקיעים, keneged zayin reki'im, משבח להקב״ה שהוא דר למעלה
מז׳, meshabe'ach le-Hakadosh Baruch Hu she-hu dar lemala mi-zayin, מנהג כשר הוא,
minhag kasher hu, וגם מצינו בקרא ב׳ פעמים ה׳ הוא האלהים גבי
אליהו. vegam matzinu bikra shtei pe'amim Hashem Hu HaElokim gabei Eliyahu.
So we can defend ה׳ הוא האלהים ה׳ הוא האלהים Hashem Hu
HaElokim Hashem Hu HaElokim but not שמע ישראל. Shema Yisrael. So here
it's interesting reconciling the גמרא Gemara with practices of repeating פסוקים, psukim,
trying to limit the גמרא's Gemara certainly to dealing with שמע Shema
specifically, not other פסוקים, psukim, although you could say if it's a
dualism concern it's always an issue, and maybe even beyond that limiting
it to cases of the מצוה mitzvah of קריאת שמע. Krias Shema.
Somebody asked me yesterday about repeating words in the middle of a
פסוק pasuk because of the ניגון. niggun. That has to do less
with these dualism concerns but more actually to do specifically about ה׳
אלהינו, Hashem Elokeinu, ה׳ הוא האלהים Hashem Hu HaElokim and saying that
twice, but those other issues about, you know, is that considered a
הפסק hefsek in the דאוונען davening or is it considered a corruption
of the פסוק pasuk to be like repeating words in the middle.
I'm not going to discuss that now but I just wanted to
signal that. Let's take a look now as we move to the
next משנה. mishna. Now if you see the first line in the
משנה mishna on ל״ד עמוד א׳ Lamed Dalet Amud Aleph is in
parentheses. האומר יברכוך טובים הרי זה דרך המינות. Ha-omer yevarchucha tovim harei
zeh derech haminus. If somebody says the good should bless You, that
is a way of heresy, often referring to some type of a
Hebrew Christian practice.
So that is in parentheses because it's in none of our texts
of the משנה, mishna, it's not in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, it does
however appear in מגילה Megillah because in מגילה Megillah the משנה mishna
we read yesterday about על קן צפור יגיעו רחמיך, al kan tzipor
yagiu rachamecha, Your compassion goes to the mother's nest, which is a
concern about, you know, is that a concern about that raised all
these issues about טעמי המצות. ta'amei hamitzvos. Anyway, that is an identical
משנה mishna in מגילה Megillah and where that appears in מגילה Megillah
it has this line that there's also some problem of saying יברכוך
טובים. yevarchucha tovim. That is not in our text, in our משנה,
mishna, it just isn't, for I don't know why, maybe what's the
problem?
Oh yeah, what the
problem is is also not so clear, maybe it's an idea that
somehow in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi it reflects again some type of a
dualism concern that maybe, you know, the good should praise God and
the evil should praise the evil sort of divinity or something of
that nature. Anyway, so we move on now to a new topic.
העובר, Ha-over, after the parentheses, העובר לפני התיבה וטעה. Ha-over lifnei hateiva
veta'ah.
Now somebody is, we just got through saying what you're not supposed
to say when you're in the middle of דאוונען, davening, and now
we're saying what happens if you actually made an error? Maybe you
made an error in the fixed text, maybe you made an error
because you were trying to add some text and it got you
confused. Okay, so what happens if you make a mistake and you're
the שליח ציבור? shliach tzibbur? So it says יעבור אחר תחתיו. ya'avor
acher tachtav.
Another person should take your place, should take this guy's place, even
if it means that, you know, one person is not doing all
of the דאוונען davening or all of the שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei.
Now presumably again it means, it could be the case of משתקין
אותו, meshaskin oto, that we feel a need to remove this person,
but it could just be the way רש״י Rashi and תוספות... Tosafot...
explain it like he just got confused and he's not able sometimes
you just get so mixed up that
you're not able to continue and you need somebody else to take
over.
Even in שמונה עשרה? Shemoneh Esrei?
Even in שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. So, fine. ולא יהא סרבן באותה
שעה. V'lo yehei sarvan b'ota sha'ah. Now somebody asks you at a
moment where this guy has, you know, is confused or can't continue
שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, we need to replace him, don't you say,
No, no, no, don't ask me. Go ask somebody else. I'm not
a good בעל תפילה. ba'al tefillah. That's not the time to be
having these shows of modesty. Okay? The ציבור, tzibur, it's embarrassing, the
ציבור, tzibur, it's inappropriate for the ציבור tzibur to be waiting without
the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei continuing. So if the גבאי gabbai asks
you, then you should say yes. Don't refuse at that moment. מהיכן
הוא מתחיל? Me'heichan hu matchil? When do you from where do you
begin you're now taking this guy's place? מתחילת הברכה שטעה זהו או
שצפבה. Mitechilat habrachah sheta'ah zehu o she'tza'pah.
You begin from the ברכה brachah that this person got confused in
or made an error in and with sufficient reason that he could
not continue. Okay, so he was in the middle of אתה חונן,
Atah Chonen, so you begin with אתה חונן. Atah Chonen. He was
in the middle of שומע תפילה, Shome'a Tefillah, you start at the
beginning of שומע תפילה. Shome'a Tefillah. Okay? So you don't go all
the way to the beginning, you don't go from the word he
interrupted, you go from the beginning of the ברכה.
brachah. What do we do with כט Kaf Tet when it says
על כל הברכות כולן אין מעלין אותו? al kol habrachot kulan ein
ma'alin oto? What? כט? Kaf Tet? And we have על כל הברכות
כולן אין מעלין אותו? al kol habrachot kulan ein ma'alin oto?
So again, I said that this is not is not necessarily this
is the way רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos explain this is that
he's not able to continue. He just got so confused he can't
continue.
Even though it says שטעה, she'ta'ah, it's a
little bit of a different case. This is that's a good point,
it says טעה, ta'ah, so you have to explain it contextually, that's
a good point, that is a good point. Okay, now,
okay where are we? Okay. העובר לפני התיבה לא יענה אמן אחר
הכהנים. Ha'over lifnei hateiva lo ya'aneh amen acher hakohanim. Now we're dealing
with the שליח ציבור. shliach tzibur. So A it's funny that we
start with the case of the שליח ציבור shliach tzibur making a
mistake before we focus in on the actual sort of, you know,
role of the שליח ציבור, shliach tzibur, but sometimes the משניות mishnayos
do this, they sort of start with the more unusual case and
then go to the more standard case. So it says העובר לפני
התיבה לא יענה אמן אחר הכהנים. Ha'over lifnei hateiva lo ya'aneh amen
acher hakohanim.
Thank you. מפני הטירוף. mipnei hatiruf.
But this explains why, the logical connection here, the שליח ציבור shliach
tzibur if they're doing ברכת כהנים, Birchas Kohanim, when they say, you
know, יברכך השם וישמרך, Yevarechecha Hashem v'yishmerecha, he should not say אמן.
amen. Why not? Because somehow we're concerned he's going to say אמן,
amen, it's going to be hard for him to go back to
the next ברכה brachah he has to begin after the ברכת כהנים.
Birchas Kohanim. Hard for us to imagine how an אמן amen would
confuse you so much, but if you're not דאווענען davening from a
סידור, siddur, right? It will distract your focus. You have to be
focused that after they're done with their ברכת כהנים, Birchas Kohanim, you're
continuing on with שים שלום. Sim Shalom. And if you're answering אמן
amen to them, you're getting your head in a different space, we're
concerned that you will get confused.
If he has a
סידור, siddur, he can, right? Yeah, we'll see that at the end
of the משנה. mishnah. ואם אין שם כהן אלא הוא. V'im ein
sham kohen ela hu. Now let's ask if you are the only
כהן kohen around. It takes for granted that if there are other
כהנים, kohanim, you do not do ברכת כהנים. Birchas Kohanim. By the
way, I should also mention the משנה mishnah assumes, as does all
the משניות mishnayos and all the גמרא, Gemara, that you do ברכת
כהנים Birchas Kohanim on a daily basis, like is currently מנהג ספרדים.
minhag Sefardim. The תוספות Tosfos and the רמא Rama have to defend
where this מנהג אשכנז minhag Ashkenaz comes from that we don't do
ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim on a daily basis. Their basic answer is
that, you know, since the ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim is like לברך
את עמו ישראל באהבה, l'varech es amo Yisrael b'ahava, and it has
this sense of sort of שמחה simcha associated with it, that actually
the רמא Rama says this, we live in, says the רמא, Rama,
in such a sort of depressed
circumstances, economically, subject to regular persecution, that we don't feel that we're
in the state of mind of שמחה simcha to do the ברכת
כהנים Birchas Kohanim except on the רגל, regel, which now you understand
why the רגל regel in particular, besides that the רגל regel is
associated with שמחה, simcha, it's associated with presence in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash and the ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim in the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. But anyway, that is not in the גמרא. Gemara. The
גמרא Gemara assumes you do a ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim on a
daily basis. Similarly, I'll just mention this as a total aside,
the אשכנזים Ashkenazim do not make a שהחיינו Shehecheyanu on a ברית
מילה. bris milah. Why not? For one opportunity to do the מצוה
mitzvah of the ברית, bris, right, with his child, certainly for the
parent it's a periodic opportunity. Why not say שהחיינו? Shehecheyanu? ספרדים Sefardim
do say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu at a ברית מילה. bris milah. So again,
the answer has to do with something like, well, maybe because the
infant suffers some pain, we don't make the שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu. But again,
it is interesting, the more constricting of these types of ברכות brachos
or liturgy or whatever that relate to a sense of joy. It
certainly reflects, you know, the difficulty that, whatever, the hardship of the
אשכנזי Ashkenazi life for hundreds of years that led to some of
that constriction.
It's hard to generalize historically, but it might be that there was
not an overriding cultural feeling living under אדום Edom as there was
under ישמעאל. Yishmael. For ספרדים Sefardim it
was
ישמעאל. Yishmael.
I'm
sorry, it's possible...
yeah well that's what I... that's a... Right, so I was right,
so I was right, right, right, right, so I
was right, I- I was assuming that maybe you're saying the sense
of depression, I think there was a reality of oppression. 100%. Right,
that's what I meant. 100%. The Jews living under Christian rule suffered
much greater oppression than Jews living under Islamic rule. Islamic rule was
mostly- well, mostly moderate Islam, although obviously there were, you know, there
was extremist Islam as well. But yes, that is definitely- that is
definitely a difference. Yes, right so...
I- I still don't understand the point. Is it that it would
be a ברכה לבטלה Bracha Levattala if it's fine for...?
I don't know if they go that far. They just somehow say,
you know, that it would not- it's not the right circumstance for
making it. Right. But it is strange that something the גמרא Gemara
takes as a for granted that they say oh yeah. But look,
mostly what תוספות Tosafot is doing is they're not changing what the
גמרא Gemara says. They're dealing with a reality that for however it
happened, at a grassroots level they stopped saying this ברכה. Bracha. And
then תוספות Tosafot has to reconcile that with the practice in the
גמרא. Gemara. תוספות Tosafot is not advocating a change of practice based
on this, he's reconciling.
Okay, so- right, so that's in terms of the ברכת כהנים Birkat
Kohanim assumes there's a daily ברכת כהנים Birkat Kohanim and it assumes
that the- there's another כהן Kohen the שליח ציבור Shaliach Tzibur won't
do it, which by the way- because it will distract him. Which
by the way is also a big assumption because since there's other
גמרות Gemaras that say that when the כהנים Kohanim do ברכת כהנים,
Birkat Kohanim, if you're a כהן Kohen and you're there and you
don't participate, you're עובר- Over what's it say? כה תברכו את בני
ישראל, Koh Tevarchu Et Benei Yisrael, so shall you bless, that if
you're a כהן Kohen you're obligated to participate in the ברכת כהנים.
Birkat Kohanim. It takes for granted that that would not apply to
the שליח ציבור, Shaliach Tzibur, that since it would not be possible
for him to do both roles, you know, because it would distract
him, then he would not. However- what? We'll get to that in
a minute. However, what if there's no other כהן? Kohen? Now we're
really stuck. So what do you do? אם אין שם כהן אלא
הוא לא ישא כפיו. Im Ein Sham Kohen Ela Hu, Lo Yissa
Kapav. Fine, skip ברכת כהנים. Birkat Kohanim. So much we're concerned that
he will be distracted and confused, again, not dealing with a סידור,
Siddur, that- that he shouldn't- there will be no ברכת כהנים. Birkat
Kohanim. אם הבטחתו שהוא נושא את כפיו וחוזר לתפלתו, Im Havtachato Shehu
Nosei Et Kapav Vechozer Letfillato, and he goes back- and presumably the
other cases as well. If he has- if he's confident in himself
that he can do ברכת כהנים Birkat Kohanim and return to his
role as the שליח ציבור Shaliach Tzibur without getting confused, then רשאי,
Rashai, then he is allowed. So the end of these cases make
it clear that there's a concern that somebody will get so confused
they can't continue, which goes back to Micha's point about making an
error and so on. Explained how רש"י Rashi תוספות Tosafot assume by
context that the error here is that somebody is not able to
continue. Okay, so I'm going to go back and discuss the ברכת
כהנים Birkat Kohanim in a little bit, but let's first see what
the גמרא Gemara says. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, עובר לפני התיבה צריך
לסרב. Over Lifnei Hateivah Tzarich Lesarev. Somebody who is at- it's interesting,
it says literally "going to be" the שליח ציבור, Shaliach Tzibur, but
it means somebody who is asked to be the שליח ציבור, Shaliach
Tzibur, he should refuse. Says, "No, no, no, don't pick me, pick
somebody else. I'm not- you know, I'm not- I'm not right for
the job." ואם אינו מסרב, Veim Eino Mesarev, and if he does
not refuse initially and he says, "Oh great, you want me to
be שליח ציבור? Shaliach Tzibur? Terrific!" דומה לתבשיל שאין בו מלח, Domeh
Letafshil She'ein Bo Melach, then he's like a- he's like a type
of a stew that has no salt. Meaning there's like no taste
to you, there's no- you know, you're a little bit of a-
what? Yeah, I don't know exactly the משל, Mashal, but somehow you
lack a certain amount of refinement. Okay, you don't understand, you know,
certain sense of דרך ארץ Derech Eretz is if you're asked to
do it, you're not the first one to rush to do it.
What?
So okay, you can fill somebody- fill it up, but it lacks
טעם. Taam. Then- ואם מסרב יותר מדי, Veim Mesarev Yoter Midai, if
he refuses too much, like you don't just make a show of
refusing, you really refuse and they really need you to be the
שליח ציבור, Shaliach Tzibur, then דומה לתבשיל שהקדיחתו מלח. Domeh Letafshil Shehiktichato
Melach. You're like a stew that has been literally burnt with salt,
has too much salt that it- it's inedible. At least the first
case it's edible. It might be edible without tasting so good, but
the second case is worse, it's inedible. They need you to be
שליח ציבור. Shaliach Tzibur. So worst case scenario, you know, minimally you
should be the שליח ציבור Shaliach Tzibur even if you don't refuse.
But the worst case is you keep on refusing and you're not
even serving as the שליח ציבור. Shaliach Tzibur. כיצד הוא עושה, Keitzad
Hu Oseh, so how should you act? פעם ראשונה יסרב, Pa'am Rishonah
Yesarev, first time you're asked you say, "No, no, no, ask somebody
else." שניה מהבהב, Sheniyah Mehavhev,
the second one you start sort of מהבהב Mehavhev like you start
moving a little bit, like you say, "All right, maybe, I guess,
whatever." שלישית פושט את רגליו, Shlishit Poshet Et Raglav, then the third
time they ask you say, "Fine, I'll go do it," and then
you go
down. תירד Tiyored and you go down. What?
During the דאוונען Davening or before?
Well, it's before they got to- presume- it doesn't say when, עובר
לפני התיבה Over Lifnei Hateivah presumably is for- we haven't even discussed
that yet, but presumably it's for the ברכו Barchu and the פורס
על שמע. Pores Al Shema. So they're asking you maybe during פסוקי
דזמרה. Pesukei Dezimra. You have to understand in the time of the
גמרא Gemara they didn't really have a פסוקי דזמרה. Pesukei Dezimra. But
okay, somehow so they're asking- but in- to apply to modern context,
they're asking you at פסוקי דזמרה, Pesukei Dezimra, right?
Why wouldn't everyone know how to do this? Well, that's why...
Probably the גבאי gabbai knew how to ask, you know who to
ask and who not to ask, but if you really didn't know
then this doesn't apply to you. This applies to somebody who's able
to but as, you know, but should not show themselves overeager as
a basic sort of דרך ארץ derech eretz should initially say no,
maybe it's better to ask somebody else and so on. So you
know, so but somebody that presumably is able to, which is why
after you've refused once or twice then you should go down. Like
the second time you should already indicate that you're prepared to do
it as long as if you get asked a third time.
Even today for ספרדים Sefardim there's no שליח ציבור shliach tzibur for
פסוקי דזמרא. Pesukei D'zimra.
Right. And in the גמרא Gemara there was no sitting around דאווענין.
davenin'. Right. And the גמרא Gemara didn't even have פסוקי דזמרא, Pesukei
D'zimra, but it was anyway it was before you began the part
that had a שליח ציבור. shliach tzibur. By the way there are
some people that, I mean this is brought down in שולחן ערוך
Shulchan Aruch and there are definitely some people that are מקפיד makpid
to do this, that you know that when they're asked they say
no, no, no, you know and then you ask, ask two or
three times. And sometimes the גבאי gabbai will say look we don't
have time to fool around, I need somebody right now which basically
is like the משנה Mishnah where they really need somebody right away
you're not supposed to go through this little
ritual.
Yes, but most people are prepared in advance that they're going to
do it.
It depends which מנין, minyan, maybe for שבת Shabbos yes and even
then it depends on the מנין, minyan, but for the weekday very
often no, no, they just need somebody right.
Well you come into שול shul as a גבאי gabbai and say
can you do it? and you're supposed to say no, then he
says it again and you say well maybe and then he says
it again and I say okay I'll do it.
Yes for sure. Well that's what I'm saying, is if it's really
urgent then the גבאי gabbai will sometimes basically say what the משנה
Mishnah says look we don't have time for this, I need somebody
right now so don't what once everybody knows
this procedure it just becomes like a pro-forma ritual. I know, but
isn't that true
about other aspects of courtesy that like you do things even though
sort of you know people sort of know what you're... Why do
I need to say thank you and you're welcome? Everybody knows. What?
How about if you say are you sure?
You've done that a couple of times.
Right, right, right, that's true.
Okay. ומה מזמינה עצמה, U'mah mazmina atzmah, that
sort of doesn't mean maybe does it?
No, I know, I think the way the מאירי Meiri translates it
like you sort of like you indicate that you're ready but you
haven't yet fully agreed.
You don't actually say well maybe, you actually sort of...
Yeah I might. I didn't mean a real maybe. Okay, maybe, whatever.
Anyway, תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. שלשה רובן קשה ומיעוטן יפה. Shlosha ruban
kasha u'miutan yafe. Three things, a lot of it is difficult, but
a little bit is appropriate, is very nice. ואלו הן, V'elu hen,
and these are what they are: שאור ומלח וסרבנות. Se'or u'melach v'sarvanut.
שאור, Se'or, what is it, sourdough, salt, and refusal. A little sourdough
makes good yeast, makes good bread, too much can ruin it. Right.
A little salt makes things taste better, too much makes it just
taste salty. And refusal, a little bit is דרך ארץ derech eretz
like you're not eager for a role of כבוד kavod but too
much gets in the way of us getting our business done. Okay.
אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, back to more strict הלכה. halacha.
טעה בשלש ראשונות חוזר לראש. Ta'ah b'shalosh rishonot chozer l'rosh. If somebody
made a mistake in the first three ברכות, brachos, a real mistake
that makes the ברכה bracha not valid, let's say you made the
חתימה chatimah incorrectly, you didn't say the right way of ending the
ברכה, bracha, so you have to go back to the very beginning
of the שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. The first three are considered a
unit, so a mistake means you blew the whole unit and you
have to go back to the beginning and we rule this way.
For example, an example of this would be you did not say
משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם mashiv haruach u'morid hageshem and you've already now
made the second ברכה, bracha, so it's too late to go and
insert it. So in that case you go back to the very
beginning. ובאמצעיות, U'b'emtza'iyot, if you make a mistake in a middle ברכה,
bracha, like you just made the ברכה bracha incorrectly or again a
mistake so that you have to go back, or for example you
don't say ותן טל ומטר לברכה v'tein tal u'matar l'vracha although that
you can always make it up in what do you call it
in שמע קולינו. Shma Koleinu. Let's say you said ותן טל ומטר
לברכה v'tein tal u'matar l'vracha when you should have said ותן ברכה
v'tein bracha and you actually finished the ברכה, bracha, some type of
a mistake that means you have to go back. So then where
do you go back to? חוזר לאתה חונן. Chozer l'Atah Chonen. According
to this opinion, we don't rule like it, you go, all the
middle ברכות brachos are considered one big unit, from אתה חונן Atah
Chonen till שומע תפילה. Shomeia Tefillah. And any mistake that you would
have to go back, you go back all the way to אתה
חונן, Atah Chonen, not what we said before, because before we just
said you're going back to a particular ברכה bracha and so
on. Including שומע תפילה, Shomeia Tefillah, right. ובאחרונה, U'v'achronah, if you made
a mistake in the last three, חוזר לעבודה chozer l'Avodah you go
back to רצה. Retzei. So this basically has three indivisible units, any
mistake that's a big enough problem that you go back, you go
back to the beginning of the unit. That's what רב הונא Rav
Huna says. רב אסי אמר Rav Assi amar אמצעיות אין להם סדר.
emtza'iyot ein lahem seder. There's no order to the middle ones. Now
what רש"י Rashi says that means is you can even say them
out of order. So if I realize that I made
a ברכה, bracha, I said ותן טל ומטר v'tein tal u'matar I
should have said ותן ברכה, v'tein bracha, so and I made a
ברכה bracha מברך השנים Mevarech Hashanim and I wake up about it
you know right after I said I don't know על הצדיקים, Al
HaTzadikim, right there I can say the
ברכה bracha of ברכנו. Barechenu. Right? If you've made a mistake in
a ברכה, bracha, make it up you know anywhere. There's no order
to the middle ברכות. brachos. Now that sounds a little bit strange.
Strange, but by the way, I'll give you an example where we
actually do, we don't פסקן pasken that way, but I'll give you
an example where we פסקן pasken there's no order to the middle
ברכות. brachot. There's the ברכות brachot of שבע ברכות sheva brachot and
sometimes you know you call up somebody to make שבע ברכות sheva
brachot under the חופה chuppah and they'll make the wrong ברכה, bracha,
they'll go out of order. So it's actually a very important הלכה
halacha to know that order doesn't matter, you know, it's not מעכב,
me'akev, the matter is not מעכב.
me'akev. קריאת התורה Kriat HaTorah is the same thing.
קריאת Kriat my
understanding you make the second ברכה bracha first for the עליה, aliyah,
you make the first ברכה bracha at the end.
Right. Right. Okay, so now. I'm pretty sure. Now, okay, so that's
what רש"י Rashi means in this opinion. We'll get back in a
minute to what תוספות Tosafot says. So, מתיבי רב ששת, mativei Rav
Sheshet, so רב ששת Rav Sheshet asks from our משנה. mishna. מהיכן
הוא חוזר? me'heichan hu chozer? משנה Mishna says if you make a
mistake, where do you go back to? מתחלת הברכה שטעה, mitchilat habracha
sheta'ah, from the beginning of the ברכה bracha you made a mistake,
which doesn't fit your opinion, right? It says you have to go
back to the ברכה bracha you made a mistake in. It doesn't
say you go back to אתה חונן, Atah Chonen, it doesn't say
you make up the ברכה bracha here, it says you go back
to the ברכה bracha you made a mistake in. So if you
look at the side, רש"י's Rashi's גרסא girsa was, they have it
in the right-hand margin, תיובתא דרב אסי. tiyuvta d'Rav Assi. That's a
contradiction of רב אסי Rav Assi because it shows you can't make
up the ברכה bracha where you are. You have to go back.
לימא תהוי תיובתא דרב הונא? Leima tehvei tiyuvta d'Rav Huna? Maybe it's
also a questioning against רב הונא? Rav Huna? So back to the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר לך רב הונא Amar lach Rav Huna who said
it's all one unit and you go back to אתה חונן. Atah
Chonen. No, אמצעיות כולהו חדא ברכתא נינהו. imtza'iyot kulhu chada birchata ninhu.
When it says you go back to the beginning of the ברכה,
bracha, it means אתה חונן Atah Chonen because I'm calling all these
twelve ברכות brachot in the middle one ברכה. bracha. So go back
to the beginning of the ברכה bracha means go back to אתה
חונן, Atah Chonen, which is quite a stretch. So what we have
here is two opinions, neither of which we rule like. תוספות Tosafot
says he disagrees with רש"י's Rashi's reading. He says he doesn't have
רש"י's Rashi's גרסא. girsa. He says the גמרא Gemara never rejected רב
אסי. Rav Assi. When רב אסי Rav Assi says there's no order,
all רב אסי Rav Assi meant is is that you can go
back to where you made the mistake. It means that you don't
have to keep it one big unit. It doesn't mean you can
make it up where you are. So אין להם סדר ein lahem
seder doesn't really mean there's no order. There is a סדר, seder,
but it's not like if you made a mistake in the middle
you throw it all out. You're able to go back to where
you made a mistake. That is our practice. If you made a
mistake in a particular ברכה bracha that requires going back, you go
back to the ברכה bracha where you made that error. That's how
we rule. Okay, so now, now I should by the way point
out since we are getting to the period of the ימים נוראים
Yamim Noraim and we just read an earlier תוספות Tosafot about that,
that a number of תוספות Tosafot in מסכת ברכות Masechet Brachot assume
that the additions we make for the ימים נוראים, Yamim Noraim, even
the later Geonic ones, right, the גמרא Gemara has המלך הקדוש HaMelech
HaKadosh and המלך המשפט. HaMelech HaMishpat. The גאונים Geonim added the זכרנו
לחיים, zochrenu l'chayim, כתבנו לחיים, katvenu l'chayim, all of those were added
in the Geonic period. We rule that if you forget those, you
keep on going because it was a later addition. It's actually a
question why we can do those altogether. We're about to see in
a minute that you're not supposed to make any additions in the
first three and the last three, and we make them for the
ימים נוראים. Yamim Noraim. But תוספות Tosafot assumes, and this is consistent
with the general Tosafotist approach about like we mentioned before about very
much embracing contemporary practice, תוספות Tosafot assumes that those even though they
came later, if you made a mistake you have to go back
to the ברכה. bracha. If you forgot to say זכרנו לחיים, zochrenu
l'chayim, you have to go back and make up the ברכה bracha
and go back to the very beginning. So we don't פסקן pasken
that way. So if you take a look at the end of
this תוספות, Tosafot, אמצעיות, imtza'iyot, he says like this.
The line starts with the word והיכא. v'heicha. It's about eight lines
from the bottom. He says והיכא שטעה בג' ראשונות v'heicha sheta'ah be-gimel
rishonot כגון שטעה בחתימתן, kegon sheta'ah b'chatimatan,
like you forgot or made a wrong ברכה, bracha, ברוך אתה Baruch
Atah you said the wrong ending, או לא הזכיר בין ראש השנה
ליום הכיפורים בברכת אבות
זכרנו, o lo hizkir bein Rosh Hashanah l'Yom Kippur b'birchat avot zochrenu,
you forgot to say זכרנו לחיים, zochrenu l'chayim, או בתחיית המתים מי
כמוך, o b'tchiyat hametim mi chamocha, או שלא אמר המלך הקדוש, o
shelo amar HaMelech HaKadosh, which is obvious, חוזר לראשונה. chozer l'rishona. You
go back all the way to the beginning of the שמונה עשרה
Shemoneh Esrei if you forgot זכרנו לחיים. zochrenu l'chayim. Okay, and then
he goes on. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot just to point out that
the הלכה halacha is you go back what, in the first three
to the beginning, last three to רצה, Retzei, middle you go back
to the ברכה bracha you made a mistake in. But תוספות, Tosafot,
so not like either of the opinions here according to רש"י's Rashi's
reading. תוספות Tosafot says that's רב אסי's Rav Assi's opinion, you go
back to the ברכה bracha you made a mistake in like our
משנה. mishna. And תוספות Tosafot even applies it to the additions, the
Geonic additions for the ימים נוראים. Yamim Noraim.
But even according to רב אסי, Rav Assi, the first three if
you make a mistake in the second or the third you חוזר
לראש, chozer l'rosh, right?
Right, that I said. So the first three you go back to
the very beginning. For the last three you go back to רצה.
Retzei. For the middle ones you do like our משנה mishna says.
You go back to the ברכה bracha you made a mistake in.
So according to that, if we say הקל הקדוש HaKel HaKadosh where
we were supposed to say המלך הקדוש, HaMelech HaKadosh,
you go back to the very... דבור? dibbur? You go back to
the very beginning of שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. That is correct. And
that everybody does agree. Right. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Back to the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, לעולם אל ישאל אדם
צרכיו, le'olam al yishal adam tzorachav, and this is the point I
was making about where you can make insertions, going back to this
ongoing theme about personal insertions. A person should never ask their personal
requests, which assumes that you can in general make certain insertions into
the שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, but you should not ask for them
לא בשלוש ראשונות ולא בשלוש אחרונות. lo b'shalosh rishonot v'lo b'shalosh acharonot.
Not in the first three and not in the last three. the
first three or the last three. אלא באמצעיות ela b'emtza'iyot in the
middle ones. Why? Because we're going to see that the middle ones
are the ברכות berachot for requests. The beginning three and end three
are not about request, and therefore it's not where you make your
personal insertions. So the גמרא Gemara says, what about? I'll talk about
them in a minute. דאמר רבי חנינא D'amar Rabbi Chanina says, קסבר
רבי חנינא, kasavar Rabbi Chanina, ראשונות דומה לעבד שמסדר שבח לפני רבו.
rishonot domeh l'eved shemesader shevach lifnei rabo. The first three, like the
גמרא Gemara said earlier, we learned from משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu that
first you praise God and then you make requests. So the first
three are praising God, right? You know, מגן אברהם, Magen Avraham, המלך
הקדוש, HaMelech HaKadosh, you know, מחיה מתים Mechayei Meitim and so on.
They're not explicitly about request. Obviously there's some implicit aspect in every
one of those. You know, you want God to do all those
wonderful things for you that you say in מחיה מתים. Mechayei Meitim.
You want God to protect you like you say in מגן אברהם.
Magen Avraham. But nevertheless, they're not explicitly about request. That is more
about praising God and understanding, you know, making a declaration about who
God is, so if you're here to approach God in prayer. So
those are the first three. You first
praise. אמצעיות, Emtza'iyot, the middle ones, דומה לעבד שמבקש פרס מרבו domeh
l'eved shemevakesh pras mirabo are like a slave asking for a some
type of a portion from his Rebbe. A פרס pras here, you
know, some people say it's a, but I think it just means
like a portion, like a portion of bread. You're begging, you know,
for something, a master from a slave from his master. Again, interesting
because we've had the מלך melech concept, here we're having the slave
and master concept. אחרונות, Acharonot, the last ones, דומה לעבד שקיבל פרס
מרבו ונפטר והולך לו domeh l'eved shekibel pras mirabo v'niftar v'holech lo
is after the slave has received the portion from his from his
master, he's then, you know, he he then thanks his master and
he and he excuses himself. Now there's a little bit of a
problem as Michael said, because certainly the middle ones are בקשות bakashot
clear. The first ones are שבח shevach is also clear. But the
assumption is what we're always told is that the last ones are
type of a, you know, not a thanks, הודאה, hoda'ah, a thanks.
But if you look at the last ones, they're not exactly that.
You know, שים שלום, Sim Shalom, שלום רב על ישראל עמך תשים
לעולם, Shalom rav al Yisrael amcha tasim l'olam,
it's a quest for peace, right? Maybe the middle one, הטוב שמך
Hatov shimcha is מודים Modim is that way. But the רצה Retzei
is accept our prayer. השב את העבודה לדביר ביתך, Hashev et ha'avodah
lidvir beitecha, return your, you know, your presence to the Holy Temple.
יעלה ויבא Ya'aleh v'Yavo is there
because it's part of רצה, Retzei, it's part of the עבודה. avodah.
Anyway, right. So it's very strange, I have to tell you, and
I don't really know a good answer to this about the idea
about why those ones are identified as a type of thanksgiving. Now
you will notice the גמרא Gemara does not say, by the last
one, it does not say, it says the first one it says
מסדר שבח, mesader shevach, the middle one it says מבקש פרס, mevakesh
pras, the third one it just says קיבל, kibel, he got his
פרס pras and then he asks his leave. It doesn't say he
gives thanks. Just says he asks his leave. So somehow, you know,
maybe it's important not to treat this as הודאה hoda'ah as thanks,
but as a way of asking leave. So to ask leave, now
you understand the שים שלום, Sim Shalom, right? sort of sort of
like, you know, שלום עליכם, Shalom Aleichem, right? so as a way
of greeting, as a way of leaving, as discussing about, you know,
peace, you know, okay so you're asking for peace for yourself. But
still, maybe it's more of asking for leave than it's explicitly about
הודאה hoda'ah about thanks. I still don't exactly get the רצה, Retzei,
I must tell you. Yes, what?
I think I mean רצה Retzei is like this is this is
it, now accept it.
Well that's also what שומע תפילה Shomei'a Tefilla is. רצה Retzei sort
of shifts from the sort of prayer aspect to specifically the God's
presence in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And again, it's not why
that now. The fact that it's not part of the I understand.
I understand, yeah, it's true. It's true. Yeah, but exact to say
that רצה Retzei is just about you're right, רצה בעמך ישראל retzei
b'amcha Yisrael is like accept the prayer. Then it's interesting to reflect
on how is that different than שומע תפילה, Shomei'a Tefilla, which is
hear the prayer, accept the prayer. And but and you know, in
my mind, the fact that רצה Retzei is not part of the
core middle speaks also to the fact that although, you know, this
question about how much is תפילה כנגד קרבנות. tefilla k'neged korbanot. And
as I've already mentioned, there's no explicit mention of קרבנות korbanot in
the whole שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. We start with ה׳ שפתי תפתח,
Hashem sefatai tiftach, you know, and therefore the even the רצה Retzei
which alludes to the קרבנות korbanot and the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
is out of the core middle part of the שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh
Esrei. It's sort of like the, you know, the afterword of the
שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. So but again, I'm not exactly sure how
it fits this model about the עבד eved and the and the
master. Now תוספות Tosafot says about this about the three beginning and
the end going to the ימים נוראים Yamim Noraim additions. If you
look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says
אל ישאל אדם צרכיו ג׳ ראשונות וג׳ אחרונות, al yishal adam tzerachav
gimmel rishonot v'gimmel acharonot, פירש ר״ח ורבינו האי, peirush R"Ch v'Rabbeinu Hai,
we're talking about the גאונים, Geonim, דוקא ליחיד אבל צרכי ציבור שואלים.
davka l'yachid aval tzorchei tzibbur sho'alim. You can ask for communal needs.
ולכך אנו אומרים זכרנו וקרובות, u'lechach anu omrim zochreinu u'krovot, right, everybody
says קרובות krovot during their שמונה עשרה? Shemoneh Esrei? That was אשכנז.
Ashkenaz. בהם בתפילה דווקא יחיד קאמר שעיקר ברכות אחרונות צרכי ציבור. bahem
batefilla davka yachid ka'amar she-ikar brachot acharonot tzarchei tzibbur. And then Tosafos
says, look, the end of the ברכות brachot are more about communal
issues than about personal. Now that's fascinating because if you look at
the ברכות brachot of the שמנה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, they're all in
the plural language. But you could argue that even if they're in
the plural language, some of them really are about you, you know,
but you're saying it in the plural language, in the communal language.
But that's like the first half of the middle ברכות. brachot. If
you look at the second half of the middle ברכות, brachot, they're
really about national needs: about השיבה שופטינו כבראשונה, Hashiva Shofteinu k'Varishona, צמח
דוד, Tzemach David, right, about the restoring of the land and of
the judges and so on. So the emphasis that the last ברכות
brachot are צרכי ציבור tzarchei tzibbur more than the middle ברכות brachot
I find as fascinating. But this is the justification for the additions
of the ימים נוראים, Yamim Noraim, but the Geonic additions. But what
I should also add, and this became a major debate between גאוני
בבל Geonei Bavel and גאוני ארץ ישראל, Geonei Eretz Yisrael, and then
between ספרדים Sefardim and אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, is, and this touches on this
ongoing theme of the personal sort of additions or the changes as
opposed to the strict form, is can you make these additions, forget
the ימים נוראים, Yamim Noraim, on like the רגלים, regalim, can you
insert these poems, these קרובות krovaitzes into the שמנה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei
and into other fixed parts of דאוונען? davening? So in בבל Bavel
the basic answer was absolutely not. We have תפילה קבועה, tfilla kevuah,
can't make those additions.
And ספרדים Sefardim basically followed the מנהג הצרפתי, minhag hatzirpati, often came
from the בבל Bavel culture, and that was very much the approach
in ספרד. Sfarad. Whereas in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, which by the
way I should say that these poems, liturgy, and the פיוטים piyuttim
are being written in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. That's where they had
this source of creativity. That's where it was part of the culture.
And there they wanted this inserted at ימים טובים Yamim Tovim at
different times because you've got to flavor things up. If it's the
same thing you do all the time, you know, it gets a
little dull and boring and it doesn't reflect the nature of the
day and it lacks a little power. So they added all of
these פיוטים piyuttim and they said, they made arguments why we could
insert these פיוטים piyuttim even into the fixed prayer, even into the
first three and the last three.
Not the one that you do right?
Yeah okay that's true I don't know exactly all the minhagim. Anyway,
people are interested, Ruth Langer wrote a whole book on this called
"To Worship God Properly", which is the debate between גאוני בבל Geonei
Bavel and גאוני ארץ ישראל Geonei Eretz Yisrael
about structure, the fixed structure versus the personalization. And here it's not
just my personal prayers, but you know the changing of it, the
shaping of it in a way that's not always about fixed structure
to give it some power appropriate for the time and for the
day. Okay and that is this sort of ongoing tension and this
is almost implicitly Tosafos just in one word saying yeah that's why
we can do this because it's a צרכי ציבור. tzarchei tzibbur. But
that was a justification and that was not fully agreed upon.
Yes I understand even why some of them are okay and some
are not. ספרדים Sefardim and אשכנזים Ashkenazim both do these זכרנו zokhrenus
and the מי כמוך mi khamokhas and all that. Yeah but not
the קרובות. krovait.
I know. So the זכרנו zokhrenus just became universally accepted. I don't
know if there was a time, I'd have to look at the
book again, I don't know if there was a time where even
that was debated.
There was a debate, if you look in the גאונים.
Geonim. Even the זכרנו? zokhrenus? Yes. Okay interesting. Interesting.
Because that's when it was still a live issue.
Right. But there was a time where that became accepted but everything
else was not as universally accepted. Right. What? I don't know look
at the book. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. That's in the גמרא.
Gemara. מעשה בתלמיד אחד שירד לפני התיבה בפני רבי אליעזר. ma'aseh b'talmid
echad sheyared lifnei hateiva bifnei Rabbi Eliezer. He went down to lead
the דאוונען davening in front of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. והיה מאריך
יותר מדאי. ve-haya ma'arikh yoter midai. He was going on a little
bit too much.
So אמרו לו תלמידיו, amru lo talmidav, his student said to him,
"רבנו כמה ארכן הוא זה!" Rabbenu kama arkhan hu zeh! Oh my
god this guy's such a שלעפער, schlepper, how long is he going
to take with his שמנה עשרה? Shmoneh Esrei? אמר להם, amar lahem,
he said to them, "כלום מאריך יותר ממשה רבנו?" k'lum ma'arikh yoter
mi-Moshe Rabbenu? Does he take longer than משה? Moshe? דכתיב d'ktiv as
it says, "ואתפלל לפני ה' ארבעים יום וארבעים לילה." va-etpallel lifnei Hashem
arba'im yom ve-arba'im layla. Okay. שוב מעשה בתלמיד אחד שירד לפני התיבה
בפני רבי אליעזר. shuv ma'aseh b'talmid echad sheyared lifnei hateiva bifnei Rabbi
Eliezer. Wait when was this prayer?
How do you know? It's about the
afterward, after the חטא העגל Chet Ha'egel when he went up to
pray for the forgiveness of בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. I
see. That's the sense, right? ואתפלל לפני ה' ארבעים יום וארבעים לילה
אשר התפללתי. va-etpallel lifnei Hashem arba'im yom ve-arba'im layla asher hitpallalti. אוכל
לא אכלתי. okhel lo akhalti.
על כל חטאתכם אשר עשיתם את העגל.
al kol chatatkhem
asher asitem et ha'egel. No,
it is clear that he was praying. I'm not saying he didn't
take a break, but okay. Alright now. שוב מעשה בתלמיד אחד שירד
לפני התיבה בפני רבי אליעזר. shuv ma'aseh b'talmid echad sheyared lifnei hateiva
bifnei Rabbi Eliezer.
There was another student. והיה מקצר יותר מדאי. ve-haya mekatzer yoter midai.
He was going very quickly. Now again one wonders by מאריך ma'arikh
and מקצר mekatzer
going exactly back to the theme, there's two ways you could do
this. Either you could schlepp on with חזנות chazzanus and go on
and on and on, or you could be adding things. or skipping
things, right? And as I mentioned, even when we had the basic
structure, the exact text, there was a period where it was still
fluid, so could be that he just said a very quick middle
ברכה bracha *berachah*, one half sentence and then ended with ברוך אתה
Baruch Atah *Baruch Atah*. So that's a question: does it mean long
and short in terms of text or just in terms of like
the חזנות *chazzanus* and the time?
Maybe, you know, did they have the practice then and you know,
everyone sort of had their own שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei, *Shemoneh Esrei*
and then they waited for everyone for חזרת הש"ץ *Chazaras HaShatz*, so
he was like maybe he finished a long long finished his own
שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei. *Shemoneh Esrei* or he just
finished very quickly, finished
in three seconds.
Yeah, yeah, okay. I wasn't thinking about that. Maybe you're right. Maybe
it means how long it was taking him to start his own
שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh? *Shemoneh Esrei*. Then you would imagine them complaining
that he was מקצר *m'katzeir*. It doesn't, I hear you, the context
I think suggests that he's doing it in his role as שליח
ציבור shliach tzibur *shliach tzibbur*, not when he's doing his private שמונה
עשרה Shmoneh Esreh *Shemoneh Esrei*. Anyway, אמר amar, ליה *amar lei*, hold
on, אמר ליה לתלמידיו *amar lei l'talmidav*, so the students said, כמה
קצרן הוא זה *kama katzran hu zeh*, oh my God, this guy's
so short, so fast! אמר להם Amar lahem, *amar lahem*, כלום קצר
הוא ממשה רבינו *klum katzar hu mi-Moshe Rabbeinu*, he's no shorter than
משה רבינו *Moshe Rabbeinu*, דכתיב *d'ksiv* אל נא רפא נא לה *Eil
na r'fa na lah*, five words for a תפילה tefilla *tefillah*. So
אמר *amar*, so אמר רבי יעקב אמר רב חסדא *amar Rabbi Yaakov
amar Rav Chisda*, כל המבקש רחמים על חברו *kol ha-m'vakeish rachamim al
chaveiro*, now we end with that פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, anybody that asks
for compassion for their friend, אין צריך להזכיר שמו *ein tzarich l'hazkir
shemo*, right, when you make a מי שברך *mi she-beirach*, sometimes this
happens for a חולה *choleh*, you know somebody who's sick, you don't
know their Hebrew name, sometimes you know you heard of somebody, you
don't even know who what their name is, so it says you
know what? God knows their name. You don't have to mention their
name in your תפילה tefilla *tefillah*, שנאמר Shenemar, *she-ne'emar* אל נא רפא
נא לה *Eil na r'fa na lah*, ולא קמדכר שמא דמרים *v'lo
kamidkar shma d'Miryam*, he didn't even say מרים *Miryam*, God knows who
I'm talking about. So that's also very important in terms of people
again going to the idea as well, you know, how much is
there a formula that has to be said? If you don't know
the name it's okay too. You were going to say something?
No, I was just thinking in terms of מקצר *m'katzeir* or מאריך
*ma'arich*, but it has to do with the text.
The text. Oh, that's interesting. Right, so that's what I, that's what
I think and it's important for us to recognize that the text
was still fluid. So again, going to this idea about using the
extremes of משה *Moshe* as examples is also very nice, it's saying,
you know, there is not one fixed way that it's appropriate to
pray. Even if you're the שליח ציבור shliach tzibur *shliach tzibbur* at
a time where there was this sort of latitude, right, there's ways
in which it's appropriate to go very long, ways very short, we're
not overly constricting, you know, the form of the prayer. Now it's
overly constricted. One has to wonder how much a printed, a printed
סידור *siddur* had the impact of completely eliminating this sense of sort
of like latitude because it all goes by the printed word and
there's loses this sort of fluid some of the fluidity that was
present. Okay, so before we continue the next point I'll just mention
that the that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, that תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafos* in
the issue about the כהנים *Kohanim*, I won't go at length, but
the תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* of מענה אמן amen. אחר הכהנים *ma'aneh amen
achar ha-kohanim*, the תוספות *Tosafos* raises the question, does the שליח ציבור
shliach tzibur *shliach tzibbur* say כהנים *Kohanim*, call them? Does he say
יברכך *y'varechecha*, does he call them at each word or not? How
much is that something that is considered a concern of distraction or
of interruption or not? So תוספות *Tosafos* goes through and has a
couple of different opinions about that, about the role the שליח ציבור
shliach tzibur *shliach tzibbur* plays in the ברכת כהנים *Birkas Kohanim*. Okay,
let's go back now to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, שלש שורות *shalosh
shuros* from the bottom, תנו רבנן *tanu rabbanan*: אלו ברכות Berachot. שאדם
שוחה בהן *eilu berachos she-adam shocheh ba-hen*, the following ברכות brachot *berachos*
are the ones in which a person bows down. Now we're really
going through some bottom line practical stuff of שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh
*Shemoneh Esrei* we have not discussed yet. So באבות ba'Avot, תחילה וסוף
*b'avos techilah v'sof*, in the beginning and ends of אבות Avot, *avos*,
right, ברוך אתה ה' *Baruch Atah Hashem*, right, מגן אברהם *Magen Avraham*,
right, at the beginning and the end, the ברוך אתה ה' *Baruch
Atah Hashem* is in the beginning and the end. ובהודאה תחילה וסוף
*u'v'hoda'ah techilah v'sof*, in the מודים Modim, *Modim* at the beginning and
the end, the מודים Modim *Modim* and הטוב שמך ולך נאה להודות
*ha-tov shimcha u'lecha na'eh l'hodos* and the ברוך אתה *Baruch Atah*, right,
we've learned before that when it's in the ברוך אתה *Baruch Atah*
you bend at ברוך *Baruch*, you're fully down at אתה *Atah* and
then you rise up at God's name. So that's where we do
our bending in שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh *Shemoneh Esrei*, that is the
הלכה Halacha *halachah*. ואם בא לשוח בסוף כל ברכה bracha וברכה ובתחילה
כל ברכה bracha וברכה *v'im ba l'shuach b'sof kol berachah u'verachah u'v'techilas
kol berachah u'verachah*, if you want to do it for all of
the ברכות brachot. *berachos* at the beginning and the end, מלמדין אותו
שלא ישחה *m'lamdin oso she-lo yishcheh*, you say don't do it, right?
If you do it in all the places it takes away the
importance about doing it where you're supposed to be doing it, then
everything is the same. All right, אמר רבי שמעון בן פזי אמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, משום בר קפרא
*amar Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi mishum Bar
Kappara*: הדיוט כמו שאמרנו *hedyot k'mo she-amar-nu*, a normal person that's like
you said, beginning and end of those two ברכות brachot *berachos*.
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol בסוף כל
ברכה brachah וברכה *kohen gadol b'sof kol berachah u'verachah*, כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol, *kohen gadol* here's an exception, right? If you are in a
very high status position, then you when you approach God have to
do even more to show that you acknowledge your humanity and that
you know that your status is not something that even plays a
role even in your presence of God, to instill a certain humility
in you. So that we demand more in terms of the frustrations,
frustrations,
prostrations for כהן גדול *kohen gadol*. So he has to do at
the end of every ברכה *berachah*. והמלך Ve’hamelech, *v'ha-melech*, and the king,
תחילה כל ברכה וברכה וסוף כל ברכה וברכה *techilah kol berachah u'verachah
v'sof kol berachah u'verachah*, the beginning and end. אמר רבי יצחק בר
נחמני לדידי מפרשא לי מיניה דרבי יהושע בן לוי *amar Rabbi Yitzchak
bar Nachmani l'didi mifarshei li minei d'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi*, the version
I heard in the name of רבי יהושע בן לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi* was the following: הדיוט כמו שאמרנו *hedyot k'mo she-amar-nu*, normal
person, those two ברכות *berachos*. By the way, I should say those
two, presumably the first one because that frames the whole שמונה עשרה,
Shmoneh Esreh. you do it at the beginning, and the last one,
the מודים, Modim. not the שים שלום, Sim Shalom, because the מודים
Modim really is the giving of thanks, so where you're acknowledging everything
that God has done and will do for you and it's the
real thanks, therefore you do it at the מודים. Modim. So, that's
what we said by a normal person. כהן גדול תחילה כל ברכה
וברכה, Kohen Gadol techila kol bracha u’bracha, the כהן גדול of the
beginning, actually the הגה Hagah says the beginning and the end, like
he raises everything one level. והמלך, the king, כיון שכרע שוב אינו
זוקף. kevan shekarah shuv eino zokef.
When he goes ברוך אתה השם Baruch Atah Hashem ברוך אתה at
the beginning of the שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esreh he stays bent down
for the entire שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esreh שנאמר ויהי ככלות שלמה להתפלל
קם מלפני מזבח השם מכרוע על ברכיו. Shene’emar vayehi kechalot Shlomo lehitpalel
kam milifnei mizbe’ach Hashem mikroa al birkav.
When שלמה Shlomo made the prayer at the beginning of the entire
inauguration of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, after this entire prayer then
it says he got up from being on his knees. So you
see he was bowed down the entire time. So we demand from
the king and the כהן גדול, you know, it's obviously power can
corrupt and go to somebody's head, so in your presence with God
you really have to, you know, use that opportunity to internalize the
sense of humility and one's humanity. All right, so now we discuss
the different forms of bowing down. תנו רבנן קידה על אפים. Tanu
Rabbanan kida al apayim. When it says ויקדו וישתחוו, vayikdu vayishtachavu, that
they bowed and they prostrated, what's bowed? So it means on your
face, like your face... some say it means your face touches the
ground, but we're going to see in a minute that you only
get down on your knees in another set of, you know, with
another type of a verb. So presumably this means without your knees
hitting the ground. I don't know how you can get your face,
unless you're very flexible, get your face hit the ground without your
knees. So some say it really just means like you just sort
of like bowed down your head. But על אפים al apayim seems
to be you're literally on your face. So it's not exactly clear,
but some say it means you just bow down your head. שנאמר
ותקד בת שבע אפים ארץ, Shene’emar vatikod Bat Sheva apayim aretz, her
face to the ground. Again, the image one gets is that literally
your face is touching the ground.
Well, can you do that without bending your knees? No, because we're
about to get כריעה kriya when it says to bow, so על
ברכיים. al birkayim. That's on your knees. שנאמר מכרוע על ברכיו, Shene’emar
mikroa al birkav, he got up from bending on his knees. So
you could have כריעה kriya and then קידה, kida, but, you know,
but this makes it sound like you could have קידה kida without
כריעה. kriya. But you could imagine, yes, that קידה kida comes after
כריעה. kriya. First you get down on your knees, then you touch
your face to the ground.
Yeah, it's not clear. It's not clear what the על אפים al
apayim means. I agree that the simple sense of על אפים al
apayim means the face touches the ground and then it would assume
that there's כריעה kriya as well, that you're on your knees. השתחוואה
Hishtachavah one minute, השתחוואה hishtachavah prostration, זה פישוט ידים ורגלים. ze pishut
yadayim v'raglayim. That is fully, not just your face touching the ground,
but your arms and your legs fully extended, you're basically like either
flat on the ground or at least, you know, your whole body...
it's not just your face that touches, you're really stretched out. And
that, right, that's ויקדו וישתחוו, vayikdu vayishtachavu, that makes sense. First the
face touches the ground, ויקדו, vayikdu, and then וישתחוו, vayishtachavu, and then
they go to a full prostration, which is often we find those
words coming
together. Okay, שנאמר הבוא
נבוא אני ואמך ואחיך להשתחוות לך ארצה. Shene’emar havo navo ani v’imcha
v’achiecha lehishtachavot lecha artzah. Will I, your mother, and your brothers come
to prostrate on the ground, which makes it sound like you are
spread out on the ground. אמר רב חייא בריה דרב הונא חזינא
להו לאביי ורבא Amar Rav Chiyya brei d'Rav Huna chazina lehu l'Abaye
v'Rava דמצלו אצלויי. dematzlu atzluyei. They sort of leaned on their side.
They didn't totally flatten themselves. We'll talk about that, now what does
that mean? What's the context? The רבנו נסים Rabbeinu Nissim quotes a
גמרא Gemara in ירושלמי Yerushalmi and this gets into the יום כיפור
Yom Kippur idea, that there's a prohibition of אבן משכית... even maskit...
ואבן משכית לא תתנו בארצכם להשתחוות עליה, v’even maskit lo titnu b’artzechem
lehishtachavot aleha, not to bow down on a stone floor, which I
mean, the פסוק pasuk is a little vague, but the way the
חז"ל Chazal understand it is outside the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash you
can't bow down flat on a stone floor. So what do we
do on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, so when you see everybody going to get those paper towels,
we assume it's because you don't want to get your suit dirty
or something, but the real reason is because of this idea that
your face and your knees should not be on a stone floor.
So the question is if you have carpeting, does that count? Right,
maybe it's the carpeting is, you know, if it's attached to the
ground does it count as it's מבוטל mevutal to the ground, does
it not? Probably it's okay with carpeting, but that's why people do,
you know, this type of a thing so it should not be
this problem. So the רבנו נסים Rabbeinu Nissim quotes the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
or understands the context here is that they had a stone floor.
They needed to... They wanted to bow down, maybe, and therefore what
they did, rather than bowing down flat, which would have been the
problem, they more did like a leaning on their side. So it
wasn't תחנון. Tachanun. No, not תחנון. Tachanun. That's the context he understands
it. Which by the way raise the question, when are you bowing
down? Which part of you know which is are they doing during
שמונה עשרה?, Shmoneh Esreh right? We never said that. We said we
said כורע Koreia which is like you know maybe maybe the knees
at most. Anyway he says it was on a תענית, Taanit, on
a fast day, a public fast day they in particular you know
like you want to show this you know greater sense of sort
of falling on falling down in prayer and did this bowing down.
It does raise interesting questions about we assume right the גמרא Gemara
said that you bend until you know your your spine you know
all of the vertebrae of your spine are bent and so on
but were there people that in a normal שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh.
actually got down on their knees? You know maybe did you know
we associate oh that's what Muslims do, that's not what Jews do
and so on but you know who knows right? Maybe there was
time for the כריעה Kriya of שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh. for some
people maybe was one of these more extensive ones and not the
simple one that we do. Okay so here you have אביי Abaye
and רבא Rava that are doing something and the context is not
clear. So תני חדא Tani Chada we talk one ברייתא, Braita, הכורע
בהודאה הרי זה משובח. Hakoreia Behodaa harei ze meshubach. If somebody bows
down at מודים Modim it's to be praised. ותני אידך Vetani Idach
הרי זה מגונה. harei ze meguneh. That's to be that's you know
that's that's unseemly. Thank you. Good translation. לא קשיא. Lo kashya. So
how do you reconcile that? לא קשיא. Lo kashya. הא בתחילה הא
בסוף. Ha bitchila ha besof. The beginning or the end. So here
the גמרא Gemara seems like you should not be doing the כריעה
Kriya at least for part of the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh. presumably
the end for part of the מודים. Modim. Why? Not clear. So
רבא כרע בהודאה תחילה וסוף. Rava kera behodaa tchila vesof. So רבא
Rava did it beginning and end of מודים Modim? like we said
before. So אמרו ליה רבנן Amru lei rabanan so the rabbis said
to him אמאי קעביד מר הכי Amai kavid mar hachi why are
you doing that? אמר להו Amar lehu given that we just said
that it's you know הרי זה מגונה. harei ze meguneh. אמר להו
Amar lehu חזינא ליה לרב נחמן דכרע Chazina lei l'Rav Nachman dechara
because I saw רב נחמן Rav Nachman doing it beginning and end
of מודים. וחזינא ליה לרב ששת דכרע הכי Vechazina lei l'Rav Sheshet
dechara hachi and I saw רב ששת Rav Sheshet doing it. It's
really fascinating that here you know you speak and we've had this
more than once about observing people's practice and learning from people's practice.
והתניא Vehatanya but don't we teach in a ברייתא Braita הכורע בהודאה
הרי זה מגונה Hakoreia Behodaa harei ze meguneh that it's unseemly to
do it at
מודים? ההוא בהודאה שבהלל. Hahu behodaa sheba'Hallel. No that's not שמונה עשרה.
Shemoneh Esrei. That's the הודו להשם כי טוב Hodu l'Hashem ki tov
of הלל. Hallel. That's where it's not appropriate. I don't know because
that's presumably more about praise and it's not about the more sense
of you know but the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei the awe is
a very big sort of aspect of the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei.
which is presumably not appropriate by הלל. Hallel. What?
Which
part of הלל?
Hallel? רש"י Rashi says הודו להשם כי טוב. Hodu l'Hashem ki tov.
Okay. והתניא הכורע בהודאה ובהודאה של הלל הרי זה מגונה. Vehatanya hakoreia
behodaa u'behodaa shel Hallel harei ze meguneh.
Whether it's the normal הודאה Hodaa or the הודאה Hodaa of הלל
Hallel so you see it's
unseemly. כי תניא ההיא בהודאה דברכת
המזון. Ki tanya hahi behodaa de'Birkat Hamazon. That's the הודאה Hodaa of
benching. Not exactly clear what it's talking about. What do you think
is the הודאה? Hodaa? נודה לך השם אלקינו. Nodeh lecha Hashem elokeinu.
Okay. Anyway
so there we have the basic sort of choreography of the bow
beginning and end which interestingly we had gotten through all of these
פרקים Perakim about שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei. and we're only now wrapping
up and saying it at the end. Okay now we get to
the wrap up of the entire first section of ברכות. Let's take
a look. המתפלל וטעה. Hamitpallel veta'ah. Somebody's davening and made an error
which we just said before right was a whole problem about you
know sending in some replacement. So
סימן רע לו. siman ra lo. It's a bad sign for you
if you're davening your own private שמונה עשרה. ואם שליח ציבור הוא.
Ve'im shliach tzibur hu. If you are the שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur
the leader of the davening סימן רע לשולחיו. siman ra l'sholchav. It's
not just it's not a bad sign for you. It's a bad
sign for the congregation okay that you represent the congregation so mistakes
that you make reflect badly on
them. מפני ששלוחו של אדם כמותו. Mipnei she'shlucho shel adam k'moto. Because
a person's representative שליח shliach agent is like who they are. And
I should say something about this. In הלכה literature שלוחו של אדם
כמותו shlucho shel adam k'moto is a standard stock phrase. You can
make an agent to do something for you to imagine make an
agent for a woman to to marry or a woman could make
an agent to receive the קידושין Kiddushin make an agent to buy
and sell property for you. Why? שלוחו של אדם כמותו. Shlucho shel
adam k'moto. Your agent is like yourself. But this line appears in
the משנה Mishna only in the context of שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur,
שמונה עשרה. The גמרא Gemara uses it in the much more sort
of legalistic context but in the משנה Mishna it appears only in
the context of the שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur and it really sends
a message which we don't have today right which sends the idea
that really the ציבור tzibur is being represented by this person. He
is bringing our prayers to God. I mean a little bit you
see that in like the תפילה tfilah. that the שליח ציבור shliach
tzibbur makes like before on ימים נוראים Yamim Noraim before the שמונה
עשרה. I am representing them. I am not כדאי kedai and so
on. You know I think for most of us we've lost that
feeling and that sensitivity to it but you see in the writings
of the ראשונים Rishonim as well when they talk about represented by
this person, he is bringing our prayers to God. I mean a
little bit you see that in like the תפילה tfilah that the
שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur makes like before, you know on ימים נוראים
Yamim Noraim before the שמונה עשרה. I am representing them, I am
not כדאי kedai and so on. You know, I think for most
of us we've lost that feeling and that sensitivity to it, but
you see in the writings of the ראשונים Rishonim as well when
they talk about who to, who should be the שליח ציבור, shliach
tzibbur, this profound sense that this is the one representing us to
God. And that idea here שלוחו של אדם כמותו shlucho shel adam
k'moto is used here in that sense of really as שליח shaliach
of the ציבור, tzibbur, the agent of the ציבור, tzibbur, and therefore
if he represents us to God and he makes a mistake, that
reflects badly on us, that's a סימן רע siman ra for us.
One second. אמרו עליו על רבי חנינא בן דוסא, Amru alav al
Rabbi Chanina ben Dosa, they said of Rabbi Chanina ben Dosa, שהיה
מתפלל על החולים, sh'haya mitpalel al hacholim, he would pray for the
sick, ואמר זה חי וזה מת, ve'omer zeh chay vezeh met, he'd
say after he finished שמונה עשרה says I know this one will
live and this one will die. אמרו לו מניין אתה יודע, Amru
lo minayin ata yode'a, where do you know this? אמר להם אם
שגורה תפילתי בפי, Amar lahem im shegura tefilati befi, if the prayers
flow off of my lips, then
then יודע אני שהוא מקובל, yode'a ani shehu mikubal, I know that
they're accepted. ואם לאו, Ve'im lav, and if they don't flow easily
off my lips, רש"י Rashi says maybe he might have been composing
his own, using his own words, not even saying a fixed text.
So if I'm stumbling and having a hard time finding the words,
then יודע אני שהוא מטורף, yode'a ani shehu meturaf, I know my
prayers will be thrown back at me, that they were not accepted.
The obvious significance in this משנה Mishna is that how our prayers
go are somewhat can be seen as a sign, you know, in
terms of how they were accepted. So if we make a mistake,
it's not looking good, right? And if we don't, you know, and
if things go well, that's a good sign. So that idea I
think is harder for us to relate to, you know, the idea
that these types of things are like, you know, it's you know,
it seems a little superstitious like, you know, if this happens oh
it's a sign that it was accepted, it's a good you know,
but nevertheless that is how the גמרא Gemara understood that, you know,
our fact that we're connecting to God in prayer, so these things
reflect to some degree whether the prayers are, you know, whether we
should whether the prayers were accepted or not.
So the facility of the שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur here is the
way the gates of prayer are open. You know, he is it's
I don't think it's reflecting on his right, right?
But you know, but I'll give an example, right, like when we
say like, you know, coming up for ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, if
the guy if the בעל תוקע Ba'al Toke'a has a really hard
time getting the תקיעות teki'os out, right? So some people feel oh
that doesn't look good, right, oh my god like, you know, maybe
our prayers weren't accepted, it wasn't. So that's superstitious.
I okay, so
how is that different than this? If the שליח ציבור makes a
mistake, that's a bad sign, our prayers weren't accepted.
It could be the, you know, תפילה בשער. tefilla b'sha'ar. I understand.
The question is how is it reflected by whether the שליח ציבור
or you or me are making mistakes or not.
It's not it's not the ability of the שליח ציבור, it's just
God has closed those gates, no one's getting in.
I know, but we are saying when the שליח ציבור makes a
mistake, it reflects that God has closed the gates.
טעה, Ta'a, המתפלל וטעה. hamitpalel v'ta'a.
I know
who's gonna
oh, you're talking about it about רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, I'm talking
about the first half of the משנה. Mishna. All right, so let's
take a look. גמרא Gemara says אהיי, Ahai, on which which one
of the ברכות because the גמרא Gemara wants to limit it, it's
interesting, they're like really you make a mistake anywhere and that's a
סימן רע? siman ra? So it wants to maybe limit it, maybe
in very particular places it's significant, this error. So אמר רבי חייא
אמר רב ספרא משום חד דבי רבי, Amar Rabbi Chiyya amar Rav
Safra mishum chad d'bei Rebbi, באבות, ba'Avot,
only if you make a mistake in אבות, Avot, in the beginning,
does that is that a bad sign. Otherwise, okay, you made a
mistake. איכא דמתני לה, Ika d'masnei la, some teach this ברייתא Baraisa
on the ברייתא. Baraisa.
What does the ברייתא Baraisa say? המתפלל צריך שיכוון את לבו בכולן,
Hamitpalel tzarich sheyechaven et libo bekulan, when you pray you have to
have כוונה kavana for all of the ברכות. ואם אינו יכול לכוון
בכולן, Ve'im eino yachol lechaven bekulan,
if you can't have כוונה kavana for all of them, יכוון את
לבו באחת, yechaven et libo be'achat, it's sufficient to have ברכה for
one of them. At which one? אמר רבי חייא אמר רב ספרא
משום חד דבי רבי, Amar Rabbi Chiyya amar Rav Safra mishum chad
d'bei Rebbi, באבות, as long as you have כוונה kavana for אבות,
Avot. the beginning, same like you do you bow down in the
beginning, that frames the whole שמונה עשרה. And this is how we
rule, that if somebody feels they weren't thinking, they were on autopilot,
they weren't having כוונה, kavana, as long as you had כוונה kavana
for the first ברכה you are יוצא. yotze. Not the first, no,
אבות. Avot, Now if you take a look at תוספות, he says
והא דאמרינן בסופר ve'ha d'amrinan b'sofer wherever לעולם יעמוד אדם דעתו אם
יכול לכוון יתפלל ואם לאו אל יתפלל, Le'olam ya'amod adam da'ato im
yachol lechaven yitpalel ve'im lav al yitpalel,
that you should assess whether you can have כוונה kavana and if
you can't then don't דאוון. daven. יש לפרש נמי באחת מהם. Yesh
l'faresh nami be'achat mehem. Really what that means is for אבות, Avot
if you can have כוונה kavana for אבות Avot, that suffices. So
תוספות takes this גמרא Gemara and limits everything to אבות, Avot. but
it's important to note that רמב"ם Rambam doesn't do this. רמב"ם Rambam
is explained by רב חיים Rav Chaim basically says that there are
two types of כוונה. kavana. Normally we talk about כוונה kavana to
be יוצא, yotze, we're not even talking about that. But normally what
you talk about the other כוונה kavana in דאוונינג davening you talk
about כוונה kavana knowing what the words mean. That's where minimally you
need כוונה kavana by the first ברכה to know what the words
mean and if you can't have that כוונה kavana you're not יוצא.
yotze. But there's another aspect to according to at least the רמב"ם
Rambam you need כוונה kavana for the entire שמונה עשרה. Not what
the words mean, not to be יוצא, yotze, but awareness that you're
standing before God. דע לפני מי אתה עומד, Da lifnei mi ata
omed, right, you know, מי אתה עומד, mi ata omed, עומדת. omedet.
So standing before God and that is according to the רמב"ם Rambam
if you don't have that at any point. Thought the first ברכה
was the only unit though. Now we're singling out אבות.
That's true. Okay. Same way we single out for the קריאה. kriah.
אמרו ליה לרבי חנינא, Amru leih le-Rabbi Chanina, we said by רבי
חנינא. Rabbi Chanina. מנין הני מילי, Minayin hanei mili, where do we
know this, that it was about being accepted, that how it flowed
off determines whether it was accepted? אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, דאמר קרא, d'amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says
בורא ניב שפתים, Borei niv sefatayim, the one who creates speech of
the lips, שלום שלום לרחוק ולקרוב, Shalom shalom larachok velakarov, peace peace
to distant and close. And he says בורא borei if it's ברי,
bari, if the ניב שפתים, niv sefatayim, your speech is healthy and
clear and good, then it's שלום שלום. shalom shalom. אמר השם ורפאתיו,
Amar Hashem urefativ,
and I will heal them, which was of course the point about
sick and being healed. אמר רב חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן,
Amar Rav Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, כל הנביאים כולם לא
נתנבאו אלא למשיא בתו לתלמיד חכם. Kol haneviim kulam lo nitnab'u ela
lemasi bito letalmid chacham.
All of the blessings that are mentioned in all of the נביאים,
neviim, that's only for somebody that indirectly connects to the sages. You
marry your daughter off to a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, ולעושה פרקמטיא
לתלמיד חכם, ve'oseh prakmatya letalmid chacham, you help a תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham in business, ומהנה תלמיד חכם מנכסיו, umahaneh talmid chacham minachasav, or
you give them some funds. That's all of those amazing ברכות are
only for people that support the תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. אבל תלמידי
חכמים עצמם, Aval talmidei chachamim atzmam, the sages themselves, עין לא ראתה
אלקים זולתך יעשה למחכה לו, Ayin lo ra'ata Elokim zulatcha ya'aseh limchakeh
lo,
an eye has never seen God, you shall do to those
who wait for you. So what they're going to get is beyond
anything we could have imagined. ואמר רב חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן, Ve'amar Rav Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, so a similar
statement here, same מן דאמר man de'amar but a different twist, כל
הנביאים כולם לא נתנבאו אלא לימות המשיח. Kol haneviim kulam lo nitnab'u
ela leyemot hamashiach. All of the blessings in all the prophets are
only for the messianic period. אבל עולם הבא, Aval Olam Haba,
the world to come, עין לא ראתה אלקים זולתך, Ayin lo ra'ata
Elokim zulatcha, that's beyond imagining. By the way, עולם הבא, Olam Haba,
what does that mean? Often we assume עולם הבא Olam Haba in
the lens of the רמב"ם Rambam means like what happens to your
soul after you die. But the early meaning of עולם הבא, Olam
Haba, and the פשט peshat meaning in the גמרא Gemara, is what
happens after the period of משיח Mashiach in this world, when this
world becomes transformed after the period of משיח. Mashiach. And תחיית המתים?
techiyat hameitim? Right.
And correct, תחיית המתים techiyat hameitim and all of that.
So now the גמרא Gemara says ופליגי דשמואל, upligi deShmuel, that argues
on שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר שמואל, D'amar Shmuel, אין בין העולם הזה לימות
המשיח אלא שעבוד מלכויות בלבד, ein bein ha'olam hazeh leyemot hamashiach ela
shibud malchuyot bilvad, that really the time of משיח Mashiach is not
going to be all this amazing blessings of all of the prophets.
There's not going to be really a difference between now and messianic
times except that we will not be subjugated to the rule of
other kingdoms. שנאמר כי לא יחדל אביון מקרב הארץ, Shenemar ki lo
yechdal evyon mikerev ha'aretz, the poor will never cease from the land.
Even in the times of משיח Mashiach there will be poor, don't
think it's all going to be a miraculous time. Now you will
notice a little letter by שמואל, Shmuel, the זיין, zayin, אין בין
העולם הזה, ein bein ha'olam hazeh, because רמב"ם's Rambam's philosophy was very
important that he reject the whole miraculous idea of the messianic period.
And therefore he ruled like שמואל Shmuel and said the only difference
will be we won't be under the subjugation of other nations. But
if you read the רמב"ם Rambam when he says this position he
says אמרו חכמים, amru chachamim, אין בין העולם הזה לימות המשיח אלא
שעבוד מלכויות. ein bein ha'olam hazeh leyemot hamashiach ela shibud malchuyot. He
turns a single opinion in שמואל, Shmuel, which is somewhat marginalized in
the גמרא, Gemara as if it were the consensus of the rabbis.
But for the רמב"ם Rambam that's very important because he was dealing
with people that were hyper-focused on messianic times and the miracles and
all that and the רמב"ם Rambam tried to distract them from that
or turn their attention away from that and he פוסק paskens like
שמואל, Shmuel, if you can פוסק pasken these things. Anyway, so now
the גמרא continues. ואמר רב חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Ve'amar
Rav Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, כל הנביאים כולם לא נתנבאו
אלא לבעלי תשובה. Kol haneviim kulam lo nitnab'u ela leba'alei teshuvah. All
of these blessings are for people that have done תשובה. teshuvah. אבל
צדיקים גמורים, Aval tzaddikim gemurim, people that have never sinned,
עין לא ראתה אלקים זולתך, Ayin lo ra'ata Elokim zulatcha, then we
cannot even imagine. ופליגי דרבי אבהו, Upligi deRabbi Abbahu, that argues on
רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu. דאמר רבי אבהו, D'amar Rabbi Abbahu, מקום שבעלי
תשובה עומדים צדיקים גמורים אינם עומדים, makom sheba'alei teshuvah omdim tzaddikim gemurim
einam omdim, that the בעלי תשובה ba'alei teshuvah are in even a
higher place than the צדיקים. tzaddikim. They were able to overcome their
sinfulness and their past. שנאמר, as the פסוק says, שלום שלום לרחוק
ולקרוב, Shalom shalom larachok velakarov,
distant and then close. לרחוק ברישא והדר ולקרוב, Larachok bereisha vehadar velakarov,
so first those that had been distant, they are the ones that
are in even a higher level. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר לך,
amar lach, מאי רחוק, mai rachok, no, what does distant mean? שהיה
רחוק מדבר עבירה, Shehayah rachok midevar aveirah, they were distant from sin,
but it means those that had never sinned מעיקרא. me'ikara. ומאי קרוב?
Umai karov? שהיה קרוב לדבר עבירה ונתרחק ממנה, Shehayah karov lidevar aveirah
venitrachak mimena, somebody that had originally been sinful, ונתרחק ממנה השתא. venitrachak
mimena hashta. Okay, מאי עין לא ראתה, mai ayin lo ra'ata, so
what does this mean, the eye has not seen? אמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי, זה יין המשומר בענביו מששת ימי בראשית. zeh yayin hameshummar
ba'anavav misheshet yemei bereishit. This is wine that has been kept in
the grape from the six days of creation, so nobody's ever seen
it. The juice has never come out of those grapes that were
around from the six days of creation, so it's עין לא ראתה,
ayin lo ra'ata, we've never seen such grapes, such juice. רבי שמואל
בר נחמני Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani אמר, זה עדן. zeh Eden.
This is עדן, Eden, Eden, right, nobody's ever seen עדן. Eden. Right,
even אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon never saw the juice from those grapes,
now saying even אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon never saw עדן. Eden. Why
not? שלא שלטה בו עין
כל בריה. shelo shalta bo ayin kol beriah. No creature ever saw
Eden. שמא תאמר אדם הראשון? shema tomar Adam HaRishon? No. היכן היה?
בגן. Heichan haya? BeGan. He was in the garden. He wasn't in
the rest of Eden. So ושמא תאמר הוא גן הוא עדן, veshema
tomar hu Gan hu Eden, you'll say it's the same, but we
tend to think that. גן עדן, Gan Eden, עדן, Eden, we think
they're all the same place. No. תלמוד לומר ונהר יוצא מעדן להשקות
את הגן, Talmud lomar: Venahar yotze meEden lehashkot et haGan, a river
came out of Eden to water the garden. גן לחוד ועדן לחוד.
Gan lechud veEden lechud. So Eden, nobody, even אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon
hasn't seen Eden. Okay, just to finish up. תנו רבנן מעשה שחלה
בנו של רבן גמליאל, Tanna Rabbanan: Maase shechala bno shel Rabban Gamliel,
the son of Rabban Gamliel got sick. שגר שני תלמידי חכמים אצל
רבי חנינא בן דוסא, Shagar shnei talmidei chachamim etzel Rabbi Chanina ben
Dosa, he sent two students to רבי חנינא בן דוסא Rabbi Chanina
ben Dosa לבקש עליו רחמים, levakesh alav rachamim, to pray for his
son. כיוון שראו אותם, Kivan sherau otam, when רבי חנינא בן דוסא
Rabbi Chanina ben Dosa saw them coming, he knew what they were
coming about. עלה לעלייה וביקש עליו רחמים, Ala laaliyah ubikesh alav rachamim,
he went up to the roof or to the second story
and prayed for him. בירידתו אמר להם, Biyeridato amar lahem, when he
came down he said to them: לכו, Lechu, go back. You don't
even need to talk to me. It's taken care of. חלצה לו
חמה, chaltsata chama, that the fever has departed from him. אמרו לו
וכי נביא אתה? Amru lo: Vechi navi ata? Are you a prophet?
אמר להם, amar lahem, he said: לא נביא אנוכי ולא בן נביא
אנוכי, lo navi anochi velo ben navi anochi, not a prophet or
the son of a prophet. אלא כך מקובלני, Ela kach mekublani, this
is my
tradition. אם שגורה תפלתי בפי, im shegura tfilati befi, if it comes
smoothly off of my lips, then יודע אני שהוא מקובל, yodea ani
shehu mekubal, I know it was accepted. ואם לאו, Veim lav, and
if not, יודע אני שהוא מטורף, yodea ani shehu mitoraf, I know
it was rejected. ישבו וכיוונו אותה שעה, Yashvu vechivnu otah shaah,
they sat down and they wrote exactly what time he said that
he had prayed and it was accepted. וכשבאו אצל רבן גמליאל, Ukeshebau
etzel Rabban Gamliel, and when they came back to רבן גמליאל, Rabban
Gamliel, אמר להם, he said to them, the people he sent, העבודה,
HaAvodah,
by God, in fact, לא חסרתם
ולא הותרתם, lo chasartem velo hotartem, it was not one minute before
or one minute after, אלא כך היה מעשה, ela kach haya maase,
it was exactly that way. באותה שעה חלתה לו חמה, beotah shaah
chalatato chama, exactly at that moment his fever departed. ושאלו לנו מים
לשתות, Veshalu lanu mayim lishtot, and he asked for us for water
to drink, which is what happens when the fever breaks. ושוב מעשה
ברבי חנינא בן דוסא, Veshuv maase beRabbi Chanina ben Dosa, one final
story, שהלך ללמוד תורה אצל רבי יוחנן בן זכאי, shehalach lilmod Torah
etzel Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai, he went to learn תורה Torah from
רבי יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai, which makes it clear
who was the bigger תלמיד חכם. Talmid Chacham. וחלה בנו של רבי
יוחנן בן זכאי, Vechala bno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai, רבי
יוחנן בן זכאי'ס Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai's son got sick. אמר לו
חנינא בני בקש עליו רחמים ויחיה, Amar lo: Chanina bni bikesh alav
rachamim veyichyeh, he said: חנינא Chanina my son, pray for my son
who is sick and he will live. הניח ראשו בין ברכיו וביקש
עליו רחמים וחיה, Hiniach rosho bein birkav ubikesh alav rachamim vechaya, he
put his head between his knees and he prayed and he lived.
אמר רבי יוחנן בן זכאי, Amar Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai, אלמלי הטיח
בן זכאי את ראשו בין ברכיו כל היום
כולו,
Ilmali hitiach ben Zakkai et rosho bein birkav kol
hayom kulo, if I had put my head between my knees that
entire day, לא היו משגיחים עליו, lo hayu mashgichim alav, they would
not have paid attention to me up in heaven. He did it
for a few minutes. If I had spent the whole day, my
prayers wouldn't have been accepted. אמרה לו אשתו, Amrah lo ishto, his
wife said to him: וכי חנינא גדול ממך? Vechi Chanina gadol mimcha?
Is he greater than you? אמר לה לאו, Amar lah: Lav, no.
אלא הוא דומה כעבד לפני המלך, Ela hu domeh keeved lifnei haMelech,
he's like a servant of the king that's always around. ואני דומה
כשר לפני המלך, vaani domeh kessar lifnei haMelech, I'm like an officer.
The officer only has meetings a few times in the year. So
he has a more intimacy with God, which is an interesting question
because it's still a question like whose request do you listen to
more, the slaves or the officers? And the גמרא actually does recognize
that there are these different personality types. The sage is not necessarily
the person who is as intimate with God in the mode of
תפילה. They do recognize that the whole phenomenon of תפילה and who
excels there is not necessarily the same as who is the תורה
Torah sage. Let me just finish. ואמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר
רבי יוחנן אל יתפלל אדם אלא בבית שיש בו חלונות. V'amar Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan: Al yitpallel adam ela bevayit sheyesh
bo chalonot. We saw this before. Pray in a house with windows.
שנאמר וכוין פתיחן ליה בעיליתיה נגד ירושלים, Shene'emar: Vechivin ptichin leh beiliyatai
neged Yerushalayim, that
the windows were open to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ורש"י v'Rashi by the way
says that you will have a sense when you're in there, מסתכל
כלפי שמיא, mistakel klapei shmaya, you see the heaven and it helps
your כוונה. kavana. אמר רב כהנא חציפא עלי מאן דמצלי בבקעתא, Amar
Rav Kahana: Chatzifa alai man dematzli bebikta,
it is like חוצפה chutzpah to me somebody who דאוונס davens in
a valley, which is a place where apparently a lot of people
are going, because it'll distract you. ואמר רב כהנא חציפא עלי מאן
דמפרש חטאיו, V'amar Rav Kahana: Chatzifa alai man demifaresh chataei, it's
also considered חוצפה chutzpah somebody who goes off like now when
everybody talks about all of their past to the whole world. He
says that's חוצפה chutzpah to me somebody who goes off and announces
their past sins. שנאמר אשרי נשוי פשע כסוי חטאה, Shene'emar: Ashrei nesui
pesha kisui chataah,
blessed is the one that covers sin, not that announces their sin.
And with that we will end these פרקים, prakim, הדרן עלך, hadran
alach, אמן.